Computer is our daily necessities. Our
计算机是我们的生活必需品
daily life is inseparable from the computer.
我们的日常生活已经离不开
Whether you
计算机了
are using the computer directly or not, you are using
不管你是不是直接在使用计算机
the computer intentionally or unintentionally,
你都有意无意的在使用计算机
or using the computer to provide you with
或者在使用计算机给你提供的
services,
服务
such as you go. Bank withdrawal ATM is a computer,
比如说你去银行取钱ATM是一
you withdraw
台计算机
money on the counter, the
你在柜台上取钱
bank’s resources are also used by the computer.
银行的资源使用的也是计算机
When we use a computer, we all need to
当我们使用计算机的时候
use the software already on the computer. For
我们都是要用计算机上面已经
example, if
有的软件
you are using a mobile phone, of
比如说你在使用手机
course, we must first say that the mobile phone is
当然首先我们得说手机也是台
also a
计算机
computer. When we want to use the
我们要用手机的时候
mobile phone, what we want is where to go. An app
我们想的是去哪找一个APP而
instead of saying that we have to write an app
不是说我们得要自己去写一个
ourselves
APP
Of course, if you searched all the
当然如果你找遍了所有的这个
markets,
市场
you can't find the APP you want. Maybe
你发现不了自己想要的功能的
you have to write one yourself at this
APP也许这种时候你得自己写
time.
一个
If you have a special request on the computer,
如果你在电脑上你有一个特殊的
you
要求
want to do a special thing, you
你想做一件特殊的事情
can't find the right software,
你找不到合适的软件
maybe you still have to write a software yo
也许你还是得要自己去写一个
urself.
软件
But this kind of thing about writing software
但是写软件的这种事情在现代
is rare in modern
已经很少见了
times, right?
对吧
Most people don't need to write their own software.
大多数的人都不需要自己写软件
So what is the purpose of our program
所以我们学程序设计的目的是
design? The
什么呢
important purpose is not to say that you
重要的目的倒不在于说你要为
have to write a software
自己写一个软件
for yourself. The important purpose is
重要的目的是说通过学习程序
to learn
设计
how to work with the computer, how the computer
你可以理解计算机是怎么工作的
is good at what kind of things, what
计算机擅长做什么样的事情
the computer can do, What kind of
计算机能做什么样的事情
thing is that computers are not easy to do or
什么样的事情是计算机不容易做
are not good at doing.
或者不擅长做的
So how does the computer generally solve the
那么计算机一般是怎么解决问题
problem?
的呢
For example, if we eat in a restaurant, just
比如说我们如果在餐馆里吃饭
sit down, I hope
刚坐下来
to drink a glass of water, I
我希望能够喝一杯水
might say to Wetter, please give
我可能会跟韦特说
me a glass of water.
请给我一杯水
Because this Viter is a
因为这个维特是人
human, he is not a computer,
他不是计算机
so just tell him, please
所以你只要跟他说
give me a glass of water.
请给我一杯水
Of course, it will know how to give you a
当然它维特就知道说怎么去给你
glass of water. He
拿一杯水来
will turn to the kitchen,
他会转身走到厨房
find a cup, pour a
找一个杯子
glass of water for you,
倒一杯水给你
and then bring it to you.
然后给你拿过来
But for a computer, if you
但是对于计算机来说
want him to do something for you, it may
如果你想让他为你做一件事情
not be as good as automation. Maybe you need
可能没有那么好的自动化的程度
to tell the computer how to do it step by
也许你需要一步一步的告诉那个
step, for example, you
计算机应该怎么去做
might say to the rig. You have to turn
比如说你可能会对钻机说
around and go to the
你要转身走到厨房
kitchen, then find a cup, then
然后找到一个杯子
find a kettle, then pour
然后找到一个水壶
some water into the cup, and finally
然后在杯子里面倒入一些水
take the cup back to the table.
最后拿着杯子走回桌子
The computer is like this. In
计算机就是这样子
fact, let’s say that he is a computer. He is
事实上我们再说他是电脑
very smart and intelligent. In
他很聪明很智能
fact, the computer will not do anything.
其实计算机什么也不会
The computer will only do one
计算机只会做一件事情
thing, that is, if you want it to be done
就是你要它一步一步怎么做
step by step, he will show you step by step.
他就一步一步的怎么做给你看
Of course, what is his greatest
当然他最大的能力是什么
ability? You told him to
你叫他做这一步
do this step, he will not
他一定不会走那一步
take that step, he will do everything you want
他会把你要他做的每一步都做得
him
很好
to do well, but he does not know how to string
可是他不知道怎么把这些步骤串
these
起来
steps to meet your
来满足你的要求
requirements, how to go Put these steps
怎么去把这些步骤串起来
together, this is what you do as a person
这就是你作为一个人要做的事情
So when I face a person, we just
所以当我面对一个人的时候
have to say what that person, what
我们只要对那个人说what
do I want you to
我要你做什么
do, and of course he knows what to do.
他当然自己就知道要去做什么
But in the face
可是面对计算机
of the computer, we have to
我们就必须要告诉它how
tell it how to
to do
do, how to make this thing
如何去把这件事情做出来
When we want to tell the
当我们要告诉计算机
computer, we want the computer to know how
我们要让计算机知道如何去把一
to make a thing, we need
件事情做出来的时候
to have a certain way, we need
我们需要有一定的方式
to have a certain means to describe this
我们需要有一定的描述这种步骤
step,
的手段
then this means is called a program
那么这个手段就叫做程序
The program is a special programming language
程序就是用一种特殊的编程语言
to write a way to express how we want the
去写出来表达我们要计算机如何
computer to solve the problem.
去解决问题的一种东西
In other words, what is the role of programming
也就是说编程语言作用是什么
language? We use a programming language to tell
我们用编程语言来告诉计算机
the computer, I want you to do it step by step,
我要你怎么一步一步的去做
how to go to the kitchen to get water to give me drink
怎么走过去去厨房取水来给我喝
So we are not using a programming language to
因此我们不是用编程语言去和
talk to a computer. We
计算机交谈的
use a programming language to write down the
我们是用编程语言去写下要
steps to do things for the computer
计算机做事情的步骤
and let the computer execute.
让计算机去执行
Conversation is another
交谈是另外一件事情
thing. If we take a computer as a person,
如果我们拿计算机当做是一个人
what
的话
is our conversation with the computer?
我们和计算机的交谈其实是什么
It’s
呢
actually the actions you usually do on
其实就是你平时在你的计算机上
your computer.
做的那些动作
For example, if you see a piece of
比如说你在桌面上看见有一个
software
软件
on the desktop, you
你想要去吸引他
want to attract him, you double click
你double click
Double click is the way you talk to him.
double click就是
You are ordering it to do
你和他交谈的方式
things. Then he runs the
你在命令它做事情
software and shows you the software
然后他把软件运行起来了
running. It is his feedback to you. This
给你看到了软件运行的情况
is a conversation, but the
那是他给你的反馈
programming language
这个是交谈
is not. Used to talk, you are not in
但是编程语言不是用来交谈的
the process of compiling a language, not
你没有在编成语言过程当中
in a programming language, he
不是用编程语言说一句
makes a sentence,
他做一句
this is not the same
这是不一样的
What language does the computer
计算机懂什么样的语言呢
know? The computer actually only knows the
计算机其实只懂我们现在屏幕上
language on our
的这种语言
screen. What you see above is a series of
大家现在在这个上面看到的是
numbers. You may feel
一连串的数字
strange. Is there a letter
你可能会觉得奇怪
here? That's right, this is a
我这里头不是有字母吗
hexadecimal
没错
number, because there is a hexadecimal
这是一种16进制的数字
number, that is, it
因为有16进制
has a number from 0 to 15, each bit has
也就是说它有从0到15的数
a number from 0 to 15, so the Arabic
每一位都有从0到15的数
number 0 to 9 is not enough. Expressed, we have
所以阿拉伯数字0到9不够表达
to
了
use the letters A to F to express the following
我们要用字母A到F来表达后面
numbers,
的数字
so there will be letters inside,
所以里面会有字母在里头
but he is still a
但他还是数字
number, this is a hexadecimal
这是16进制的数字
number, this is a
这是一个
This is a program that a computer can understand,
这是一段计算机能够懂的程序
written in a language that the computer knows.
用计算机懂的语言写的
Obviously this program is
显然这一段程序摆给你
for you, and it is
摆在我们面前
in front of us. No
谁也看不懂
one can understand
我也看不懂
it. I don't understand it. I don't
我也不知道这里面具体一开始C
know what it means to be the CFFA.
FFA这些到底指的是什么样的
Because
意思
this piece of program is converted from
因为这一段程序是通过另外的
something
一个软件
we can understand through
或者说通过一个工具
another piece of software, or through a
从我们能够看懂的东西转换过来
tool,
的
what he used to be like this
他原来的样子是这样的
Of course, before you learn any programming
当然在你学习任何编程语言之前
language, this paragraph may still be like
这一段文字对你来说也可能还是
a book for you.
像天书一样
Although you can probably guess what kind
虽然你大概能够猜一猜这里面
of things may be there, what
可能有些什么样的东西
is this program doing? This program
这一段程序是做什么呢
is to use the 辗 division method to
这段程序是在用辗转相除法去
calculate two numbers,
计算两个数
which is the greatest common divisor of
也就是这儿的32和26它们的
32 and 26 here.
最大公约数
So what you see is this program, although
所以你看到的是这一段程序
this program is that we say that it is
虽然这段程序是我们说这是用人
written in human programming
用编程语言写的
language, but can you understand that
但是你能不能理解他还有程序
there is another thing on the
之上的另外一个东西
program, we are now listed on the left,
这个东西我们现在列在左边
The series of texts listed on the right,
列在右边的这一系列的文字
the text of this series,
这一系列的文字
we call it the algorithm, we
我们把它叫做算法
have to calculate the same
我们要去计算一样
Things we need to have steps,
事情我们需要有步骤
we have to tell the computer how to do it,
我们要告诉计算机怎么去做
just like before going to the
就像前面去端水一样
water, we have to have a step by step step to
我们要有有条理的一步一步的
tell the computer, we
步骤告诉计算机
tell the computer that if you
我们告诉计算机说
find that one is already equal to 0, Then we
如果你发现于一已经等于0了
will finish the oil is the greatest common
那我们就算完了油就是最大
divisor.
公约数
If V is not equal to 0,
如果V不等于0
we have to do a series of complicated calculations.
我们要去做一系列的复杂的计算
After we finish, we have to go back to the
算完之后我们还要回到第一步
first step, so that we can continue to
这样子能够不断地算下去
calculate and finally get a result.
最后能够得到一个结果
Some of thes
这样的一些描述就叫做算法
So what you see in the computer is the kind of
所以你看计算机能懂的是那种
binary stuff, and then
二进制的东西
this is what the computer knows, right? Then
然后这是计算机懂的东西
this is something
对不对
that people can understand, but this is
然后这是人能够懂的东西
what programmers can understand. This is something
但是这是程序员能够懂的东西
that people who have learned programming can understand.
这是学过编程的人能够懂的东西
On the Internet is something that ordinary people
在网上才是普通人都能够懂的
can
东西
understand. This is how to do the calculation,
这是如何去做计算的步骤
that is, the algorithm.
也就是算法
There are many steps in the middle of everything from
从算法到程序到计算机能够运行
algorithms
的东西
to programs to things that computers
这中间有很多的步骤
can run. There are many things to do.
有很多的事情要去做
So we have to let the computer do the calculations,
所以我们要让计算机去做计算
we need to find the calculation steps like this,
就需要像这样去找出计算的步骤
and then the programmer will write it out.
然后由编程员去写出来
Everything we do with a computer is called calculation. It is
我们把计算机做的所有的事情都
not that only
叫做计算
addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division
不是说只有加减乘除
are performed. Arithmetic operations are called
做算术运算才叫做计算
calculations. All things that are done by computers are calc
所有由计算机去做的事情都是
ulations.
计算
Including calculating your
包括算算你的生日
birthday, including drawing a
包括画一幅图
picture, including showing you a movie,
包括给你看一本电影
this is all calculations,
这都是计算
as long as the computer does things are calculations.
只要是计算机做的事情都是计算
The calcula
计算的步骤就是叫做算法